Guide to the Ulysse Rouchon Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Ulysse Rouchon collection
1571-1957
MS 873
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
(3 boxes)
This collection consists of documents, manuscripts and pamphlets related to the history, culture and government of the Department Haute-Loire in France and to the city of Puy.
Rouchon, Ulysse
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Martinus Nijhoff in 1965-1966.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains letters to Ulysse Rouchon; documents and manuscripts related to the Department Haute-Loire in France, its capital Puy, and the natives of this region; miscellaneous pamphlets related to the same Department and consisting of decrees, public announcements, circular letters, pastoral letters, proclamations, petitions, court appeals, patriotic songs, and materials concerning the princes and counts of Polignac, other local aristocracy and gentry, clergy, industry, commerce, tariffs, roads, military conscriptions, and religious and public festivals. Also included are miscellaneous printed materials and notes referring to the same region, and arranged according to their respective subjects of anthropology, fine arts, folklore, linguistics, literature, philosophy, religion, and traditions.
Biographical / Historical
Ulysse Rouchon resided in Le Puy (Haute-Loire). He was a corresponding member of the Institut de France and a member of the Comité des Travaux Historiques au Ministère de l'éducation Nationale.
Europe; France -- Politics and government; Haute-Loire (France); Le Puy (Haute-Loire, France)
- Inventory, 1571-1957; 3
  - Manuscripts
    Arrangement
    (Listed in the descending order of the relative importance of their creators, and within that order chronologically.)
    - France. Ministry of War. Certificates of permanent discharge from military service for Louis Boudon, Joseph Duranton, Jean Fayolle, Jean Laniel, and Claude Saby, 4 pieces, 1818 (Box 1)
    - France. Army.
      - Roll of soldiers of the company of Captain Monfroud, garrisoning Polignac Castle in the service of the King [Henry IV from the House of Bourbon, 1589-1610], with certification of the delivery of their pay, Polignac Castle, 1piece, 1590 March 15 (Box 1)
      - Report of facts vindicating the conduct of Lieutenant General Baron Mouton-Devernet, included in the order of the King [Louis XVIII from the House of Bourbon, 1814-1824] of 24 July 1815, manuscript document of 30 pages misbound in a volume so that pages 3-6 are between pages 26 and 27, believed to be written by the baron himself (Box 1)
      - Certification of honorable service of Robert Perrin in the Corps of Chasseurs of Henry IV, issued by Colonel Count d'Espinchal, Lyon, 1 piece, 1819 July 22 (Box 1)
    - France. National Guard. Mobilization order for grenadier Claude Jouvehomme, alias Georget, Puy, 1 piece, 1815 June 13 (Box 1)
    - France. Province of Languedoc. Generality of Montpéllier. Office of Tax Adjustment. Circular letter to M. Pascal from Pradelles regarding his tax matters, Montpéllier, 1 piece, 1746 May 25 (Box 1)
    - France. Department of Haute-Loire [before 1790 = Province of Languedoc. County of Velay] Town of Puy
      - Inventory of the town hall archives containing the abstracts of charters, letters patent, certificates, and deeds through which various popes, kings, and bishops granted or confirmed the privileges of the town, 1 volume of 192 pages or 96 leaves, 1654 (Box 1)
      - Register enumerating the heads of families of the town and community, and assessing their households for tax purposes, 1 volume of 386 pages or 193 leaves, 1697 (Box 1)
      - Register containing written accounts of meetings of the trustees of the parish church of St. Pierre le Monastier, and of their periodic elections from among the parishioners; the meetings dealt with practical matters, such as the maintenance of the church, its decoration, inventories of movable equipment, examination of invoices and authorization of their payment, examination and certification of accounts of the church, care of orphans, burials in the church (tombs); overseeing of the church's secular property (lands, leases, rents), etc.; 1 volume of 286 pages or 143 leaves, 1748-1790 (Box 1)
      - Circular letter of the Collector of Almshouses [? = Receveur des Hospices] to M. Montbel, lace merchant of Puy, concerning the alienation of rents due to the town almshouses, Puy, 1 piece, 1822 February 16 (Box 1)
      - Free passport of Jean Malfrey, issued by the sub-prefecture of Yssingeaux, a part of Puy, Yssingeaux, 1 piece, 1833 May 4 (Box 1)
      - Voter's cards of Jean Bonnefoy, Francois Decroix, and Antoine Souvignet, belonging to the electoral college of the 3rd district, 3 pieces, 1834 (Box 1)
      - Fragment of a draft of a letter written in the name of the members of the Civil Court of Puy to the Bishop of Puy, 1 piece [perhaps second half of the 18th century, possibly after 1789], Undated (Box 1)
      - Clet, Antoine, 1709-?. Printer and playwright of Puy. Modern transcript of three plays by Clet, copied from the original manuscript deposited in the library of the "Société d'agriculture, sciences et arts de la Haute Loire": "Le sermon Manqué," written in 1749; "Monsieur Lambert," written in 1757; "Le Borgne," written at an unknown time., 1749, 1757, undated (Box 1)
    - France. Department of Haute-Loire Vicinity of Puy
      - Manorial register (cadaster) listing the rents due by tenants from the lands belonging to the Abbey of Doe [in spite of great effort could not be identified, perhaps the modern spelling is different], situated somewhere in the vicinity of Puy, 1579, 1 booklet of 40 pages or 20 leaves; with an inserted small booklet summarizing the rents due by tenants from the lands belonging to an unidentified owner, 1 booklet of 16 pages or 8 leaves, 1571., 1571, 1579 (Box 1)
      - Register of rents due from the lands of the Viscount of Polignac, and of payments rendered by the tenants of those lands since Christmas 1758 unti St. John's Day 1764, and in the following years. Involved are lands, woods, and mills in the following villages lying in the vicinity of Puy: Chalancon, Crapone, D'Eyravas, Dous Souls, Loude, Polignac, St. Paulien, Solignac, Voutte; 1758-1790, 1 large booklet of 96 pages or 48 leaves (Box 1)
    - France. Department of Haute-Loire District of Brioude. Circular letter of the local committee of the Paternal Association of Knights of the Royal and Military Order of St. Louis and of Military Merit to Viscount of Crozèt, former Lieutenant Colonel of the Cavalry Regiment of the Prince of Ligne, soliciting funds for the relief of widows and children of fallen comrades in arms, Brioude, 1 piece, 1819 August 14 (Box 1)
    - France. Miscellaneous
      - Letter (ALS) of M. de la Rochette, Count of Rochegonde, to the Chief Editor of La Montague, forwarded by the latter to M. Ulysse Rouchon, Amiens, 1 piece with an envelope, 1956 December 2 (Box 1)
      - Letter (ALS) of M. de 1a Rochette, Count of Rochegonde, to M. Ulysse Rouchon, with an enclosed transcript of the testament of Hugues Guigues de la Rochette from 1360, a postcard of the castle de la Rochette, and ibliographical notes concerning the de la Rochette family; Amiens, 1 piece with enclosures, 1957 January 19 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets
    - Collection of miscellaneous French pamphlets related by their contents to the Department of Haute-Loire, consisting of decrees, public announcements, circular letters, proclamations, pastoral letters, petitions, patriotic songs, court appeals, etc., and concerning peace treaty texts, convocations of municipal councils, clergy, industry, expositions, markets, new weights and measures, religious and public festivals, conscriptions of military recruits, maintenance of roads, tariffs, gentry, and various affairs of the town of Puy, 3 bundles and 1 little bundle, 1789-1869 (Box 1)
    - Collection of miscellaneous French pamphlets concerning the family of the princes and counts of Polignac, peers of France, and their political and ecclesiastical activities, 1 bundle, 1730-1830 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1745-1924
    - Collection of miscellaneous printed materials and manuscript notes referring to the town of Puy and its vicinity; it consists of various pamphlets, reprints of articles, parts of books, manuscript notes on various subjects included in the collection, manuscript charts, tabulations, letters. Some of those printed materials are dedicated by the authors to various persons (Arhould, Liétard, Rouchon). All the materials are arranged according to their respective subjects, and deposited in original filing boxes in alphabetical order as follows: (Box 2)
      - File Box 1: Arts, Beaux Arts, Anthropologie (Box 2)
      - File Box 2: Anthropologie (Box 2)
      - File Box 3: Anthropologie (Box 2)
      - File Box 4: Anthropologie (Box 2)
      - File Box 5: Linguistique, Patois (Box 2)
      - File Box 6: Linguistique, Patois (Box 3)
      - File Box 7: Littérapture (Box 3)
      - File Box 8: Philologie, Linguistique (Box 3)
      - File Box 9: Philosophie et Religion, Philosophie des Science (Box 3)
      - File Box 10: Traditions, Folklore, et divers (Box 3)